STEFANO CASTRO TOGNINI

Oak Ridge National Laboratory

@ togninis@ornl.gov

Stognini

in stognini



Research Scientist at Oak Ridge National Laboratory working on computational High Energy Physics (HEP). His main efforts are focused on Celeritas, a GPU Monte Carlo (MC) detector simulation code for HEP that will enable the use of DOE's Leadership Computing Facilities—such as Frontier and Summit—by HEP experiments. In the past he was a collaborator on MINOS and NOvA, managed by Fermi National Accelerator Laboratory (Fermilab). These are long-term multi-million dollar endeavors built to understand the nature of neutrinos and answer fundamental questions related to astrophysics, dark matter, and more. His 7+ years of experience, working with diversified teams led to many published data analyses, all developed using C++, Python, ROOT, shell scripting, massive parallel computing, and MC simulations. Software development is managed using GIT, allied with automated code referencing (Doxygen). Production of technical documentation is routinely done. He also has experience teaching at undergraduate level, mentoring graduate students, presenting technical seminars, and talking to the public at science outreach events.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Research Scientist

Scalable Engineering Applications

Computational Sciences and Engineering Division

Oak Ridge National Laboratory

2023 — Present

Oak Ridge (TN), U.S.

Postdoctoral Research Associate

HPC Methods for Nuclear Applications

Nuclear Energy and Fuel Cycle Division

Oak Ridge National Laboratory

2019 − 2023

Oak Ridge (TN), U.S.

COLLABORATIONS

Celeritas Project

github.com/celeritas-project

2020 - Present

ORNL

A GPU Monte Carlo particle transport code for HEP experiments.

DOE CODE: 10.11578/dc.20221011.1

URL Muon Detector Project

2020 - Present

ORNL

A compact muon detector apparatus developed to test and validate new non-destructive techniques for geological disposal safety assessments (GDSA).

NO ν **A Experiment**

% novaexperiment.fnal.gov

2013 − 2018

♀ Fermilab / ANL / UFG

Leading author of Phys. Rev. D 99, 122004.

• Contributed to Phys. Rev. D 104, 012014.

MINOS/MINOS+ Experiment

www-numi.fnal.gov

2011 - Present

Fermilab / ANL / UFG

• Contributed to Phys. Rev. D 91, 112006 / Phys. Rev. D 93, 052017.

PUBLICATIONS

SOFT SKILLS

Teaching Mentoring Science outreach Portuguese (native) **English** Italian **French**

HARD SKILLS

Technical skills

Data analysis | Monte Carlo simulation Data structuring Parallel computing

Programming & scripting languages

Pvthon SOL C/C++ Shell

Frameworks, libraries & tools

ROOT art GIT Doxygen Geant4 **CORSIKA** Spack LSF **TORQUE**

EDUCATION

Ph.D. in Physics - High Energy Physics

Federal University of Goias

Funding: CAPES, CNPq, ANL

2012 − 2018 **♀** Goiania (GO), Brazil **DOE** OSTI www.osti.gov/biblio/1468447

M.Sc. in Physics – High Energy Physics

Federal University of Goias

Funding: CAPES, Fermilab

2010 − 2012 **♀** Goiania (GO), Brazil

B.Sc. in Physics

Federal University of Goias

2005 − 2009

♀ Goiania (GO), Brazil

i iNSPIRE HEP | inspirehep.net/authors/1074966